Gutto. Today's דף daf is קלז, kuf lamed zayin, 137 and we
pick up with the משנה. mishna. Okay, so we had discussed all
the various things aspects about doing the ברית מילה brit milah on
שבת, Shabbat, what type of cases override שבת, Shabbat, and when you
go back if you didn't finish it, all those variations. And now
we talk about an interesting case about somebody who made a mistake.
Let's take a look. משנה קלז עמוד א. Mishna kuf lamed zayin
amud aleph. Famous debate of רבי אליעזר Rabbi Eliezer and רבי יהושע.
Rabbi Yehoshua. מי שהיו לו שני תינוקות אחד למול אחר השבת ואחד
למול בשבת. Mi she-hayu lo shenei tinokot echad lamul achar ha-shabbat ve-echad
lamul ba-shabbat. You had two infants, you were the מוהל mohel presumably,
and you had one that was supposed to get the ברית מילה
brit milah on Sunday and one on שבת. Shabbat. ושכח Ve-shakhach and
you made a mistake, you forgot which was which. ומל של אחר
השבת בשבת. U-mal shel achar ha-shabbat ba-shabbat. You did the Sunday one
on שבת. Shabbat. So you were thinking you had license to do
a ברית מילה brit milah today on שבת, Shabbat, actually you did
for a different infant, but you did the wrong one, and when
you actually did the ברית מילה brit milah now you actually you
weren't even יוצא yotzei for this one because it was on the
seventh day. So what's the הלכה? halacha? So the הלכה halacha is
חייב, chayav, you are חייב chayav a קרבן חטאת, korban chatat, you
violated שבת. Shabbat. You were שוגג, shogeg, nobody said you were מזיד,
meizid, but you made a mistake and you were שוגג, shogeg, you
violated שבת. Shabbat. Okay, now let's say it was the reverse. אחד
למול בערב שבת ואחד למול בשבת. Echad lamul be-erev shabbat ve-echad lamul
ba-shabbat.
One to do on Friday and one to do on שבת. Shabbat.
ושכח Ve-shakhach and you also made a mistake, somehow you didn't do
the Friday one on שבת. Shabbat. You could have said you mixed
them up, you did the שבת Shabbat one on Friday and the
Friday one on שבת, Shabbat, which would be the most likely scenario,
but in that case when it would have come שבת Shabbat you
would no longer have been under any license to do a ברית
מילה brit milah because the שבת Shabbat one would have already been
done from ערב שבת. erev Shabbat. So the actual case is somehow
you didn't do anything on Friday and it came to שבת, Shabbat,
you somehow did not have the time to do the Friday one
on שבת. Shabbat. So now it's שבת Shabbat and now you have
license to do one and not the other. Similar scenario, except what?
The first case was you did it a day earlier. This case
was you did it a day later. Okay, it came שבת Shabbat
and now you have an eighth day ברית bris to do for
one baby and you have a ברית bris you should have done
yesterday, you didn't get around to, to do for the other baby,
which you're not allowed to do on שבת. Shabbat. What?
Nobody else told
him this is advice.
So the גמרא gemara will discuss that, but for now we'll assume
you're the only מוהל mohel around. Okay. ושכח ומל של ערב שבת
בשבת. Ve-shakhach u-mal shel erev shabbat ba-shabbat. So you made a mistake
and you did the Friday one on שבת. Shabbat. So it's similar
to the other case, except here not only did you have a
license to do it for the one child and you did it
accidentally for the other, but the one you accidentally did it for,
you actually wound up doing a מצוה mitzvah of ברית מילה. brit
milah. Not an eighth day ברית מילה, brit milah, it was a
ninth day ברית, milah, but at least you did a מצוה. mitzvah.
And it's different than the last
case. The first case, when you did Sunday's today on שבת, Shabbat,
a seventh day מילה milah is nothing. Here it's a ninth day
מילה, milah, so at least it's a מצוה mitzvah of ברית מילה,
brit milah, although it should not have warranted violating שבת. Shabbat. So
in this case רבי אליעזר מחייב, Rabbi Eliezer mechayev, רבי אליעזר Rabbi
Eliezer says you still bring a קרבן חטאת, korban chatat, מחייב חטאת.
mechayev chatat. ורבי יהושע פוטר, Ve-rabbi Yehoshua poter, רבי יהושע Rabbi Yehoshua
says you're פטור. patur. And as the גמרא gemara explains the position
of רבי יהושע, Rabbi Yehoshua, it's טעה בדבר מצוה ועשה מצוה פטור.
ta'a bidvar mitzvah ve-asa mitzvah patur.
You made an error in the doing of a מצוה, mitzvah, something
that you were allowed to have done on שבת, Shabbat, and you
made a mistake, and you violated שבת, Shabbat, but in that violation
of שבת Shabbat you actually wound up still doing a מצוה. mitzvah.
So even in your violation, it was partly in the performance of
a מצוה. mitzvah. Therefore that is enough to say you don't have
to bring a חטאת. chatat. You still violated, nobody's saying you're not
violated, but you're פטור patur from a חטאת. chatat. So another example
would be let's say you picked up your לולב lulav to take
it on שבת Shabbat and you accidentally took it outside into the
רשות הרבים. reshut ha-rabbim. Okay, so that's a case also the גמרא
gemara discusses, משנה mishna discusses, where you didn't even have a license
to violate שבת Shabbat for לולב, lulav, but still in your violation
of שבת Shabbat you were erring because you were involved in doing
a מצוה, mitzvah, you forgot yourself and you were doing a מצוה
mitzvah and you actually did a מצוה. mitzvah. So even though it
was a violation of שבת, Shabbat, according to רבי יהושע, Rabbi Yehoshua,
טעה בדבר מצוה ועשה מצוה, ta'a bidvar mitzvah ve-asa mitzvah, you are
פטור patur from a קרבן חטאת. korban chatat. Again, nobody says it's
מותר, mutar, nobody says you didn't violate, but at least you do
not have to bring a sin offering.
So he should have done optimally then just wait till Sunday and
do the Friday one two days late?
Yeah, yeah, what he should have done was once it's late, he
should have done it Sunday, but you didn't, but at least when
you did it, you did a מצוה. mitzvah. Okay now I should
note by the way that it's interesting that the same רבי אליעזר
Rabbi Eliezer whom we heard from a few days ago, who said
that you could do מכשירי מילה, makhshirei milah, that if it becomes
שבת Shabbat and you have an eighth day baby, you can go
ahead and you can go start fashioning a knife and carrying a
knife through רשות הרבים reshut ha-rabbim in order to do a ברית
מילה, bris milah, that's for the baby you have a מצוה mitzvah
to do a ברית מילה bris milah for. But if you make
a mistake and do it for another baby, then he says you're
חייב חטאת, chayav chatat, so here he is more stringent.
It's a good practice, I know you probably said it, if he
does it a day early?
If you do it a day early it does not count as
a מצוה. mitzvah. If you do it a day late it does
count.
So what do you do?
So you do הטפת דם ברית hatafat dam brit on the next
day.
You have to do...
Well yeah, that on שבת? Shabbos? No, no, no, not on שבת.
Shabbos. No, you don't do הטפת דם ברית Hatafas Dam Bris on
שבת. Shabbos. Okay, let's take a look at the גמרא. Gemara. Anyway,
part of it depends on the מסקנא Maskana of the previous סוגיא.
Sugya. That's okay. רב הונא מתני חייב, Rav Huna masni chayav, רבי
יהודה מתני פטור. Rabbi Yehuda masni patur. רב הונא Rav Huna says
you're חייב chayav and רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda says you're פטור. patur.
Now what does that mean? So it's the meaning of the first
case of the משנה Mishnah that everybody agrees on. רב הונא Rav
Huna says you're חייב chayav because you did the shop- you did
the Sunday one a day early. That's the way we have our
משנה. Mishnah. רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda says פטור. patur. That's strange. Why
if you did it a day early would you be exempt? So
we'll find out that רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda has a different version
of what the first case of the משנה Mishnah is. Let's first
focus on רב הונא, Rav Huna, that's our version of the משנה,
Mishnah, then we'll better understand רבי יהודה. Rabbi Yehuda. רב הונא מתני
חייב. Rav Huna masni chayav. רב הונא Rav Huna says at the
first case of the משנה, Mishnah, which is the sha- the Sunday
one done on שבת, Shabbos, everybody says you're חייב. chayav. דתניא, Detanya,
and here's the ברייתא Braisa that supports that version of the debate
of רבי יהושע Rabbi Yehoshua and רבי אליעזר. Rabbi Eliezer. אמר רבי
שמעון בן אלעזר לא
נחלקו רבי אליעזר ורבי יהושע על מי שהיו לו שני תינוקות אחד
למול בשבת ואחד
למול לאחר שבת ושכח ומל של לאחר שבת בשבת,
Amar Rabbi Shimon ben Elazar lo
necheliku Rabbi Eliezer ve'Rabbi Yehoshua amisha hayu lo beis tinokos echad lamul
be'shabbos ve'echad lamul be'achar shabbos veshachach umal shel achar shabbos be'shabbos, שהוא
חייב. shehu chayav. Everybody agrees in that case you're חייב chayav because
that was טעה בדבר מצוה ta'as devar mitzvah ולא עשה מצוה. velo
asa mitzvah. At the end of the day, when you did the
Sunday one on שבת, Shabbos, it was a day early, you did
not do a מצוה. mitzvah. Everybody agrees you're חייב. chayav. על מה
נחלקו? Alman necheliku? What did they
disagree? על מי שהיו לו שני תינוקות אחד למול בערב שבת ואחד
למול בשבת ושכח ומל של ערב שבת בשבת. Amisha hayu lo beis
tinokos echad lamul be'erev shabbos ve'echad lamul be'shabbos veshachach umal shel erev
shabbos be'shabbos. That's טעה בדבר מצוה ta'as devar mitzvah ועשה מצוה ve'asa
mitzvah because you did at least the- it was on the ninth
day, not the eighth day, but at least you did a מצוה.
mitzvah. In that case, שרבי אליעזר מחייב חטאת, she'Rabbi Eliezer mechayev chatas,
רבי אליעזר Rabbi Eliezer says you bring a חטאת, chatas, ורבי יהושע
פוטר, ve'Rabbi Yehoshua poter, and רבי יהושע Rabbi Yehoshua exempts. ושניהם לא
למדו אלא מעבודה כוכבים, Veshenehem lo lamdu ela me'avodah kochavim, and
both of them learned it from עבודה כוכבים. avodah kochavim. Weren't expecting
that, I bet. Okay, because what- the case in the תורה Torah
what speaks about bringing a חטאת, chatas, it speaks- it's a פרשה
parsha about עבודה זרה. avodah zarah. So that serves as a paradigm
of when you bring a חטאת. chatas. So the question is, what
constitutes, what are the salient characteristics that you identify in the case
of עבודה זרה avodah zarah to determine whether you bring a חטאת
chatas or not by other cases? So let's take a look. רבי
אליעזר סבר כעבודה כוכבים, Rabbi Eliezer savar ke'avodah kochavim, like a standard
case of עבודה זרה. avodah zarah. בשוגג. Bishogeg. מה עבודה כוכבים אמר
רחמנא לא תעביד וכי עביד מחייב הכא נמי לא שנא. Mah avodah
kochavim amar rachmana lo sa'avid ve'chi avid mechayev hacha nami lo shna.
The עבודה זרה avodah zarah is a thing the תורה Torah says
don't do it,
when you do it you bring a חטאת, chatas, הכא נמי לא
שנא, hacha nami lo shna, here too. So that's pretty simple. It's
a negative prohibition. Now of course there's other aspects to it, of
course it's something that you're חייב כרת chayav kares for or worse,
but anyway that's all that I care about is that you transgressed.
רבי יהושע, Rabbi Yehoshua, רבי יהושע Rabbi Yehoshua says no, התם דלאו
מצוה, hasam delav mitzvah,
there it was an עבירה aveyrah you did, not in the context
of doing or performing a מצוה. mitzvah. הכא מצוה, Hacha mitzvah, here
you did a מצוה. mitzvah. So again, it's pretty funny to say
you learn it from עבודה זרה, avodah zarah, but the point is
רבי יהושע Rabbi Yehoshua just feels that if you're doing, you wound
up doing this sin in the context of trying to do a
מצוה mitzvah and actually succeeding in doing a מצוה mitzvah in the
context, that's not your classic case of a חטאת. chatas. Okay, that's
the version we have in the משנה, Mishnah, that the- that the
first case everybody agrees on. What does everybody agree? When you did
the Sunday one on שבת, Shabbos, everybody agrees you're חייב. chayav. רבי
יהודה מתני פטור. Rabbi Yehuda masni patur. רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda says
no, the first case everybody agrees you're exempt, but it's a different
case. דתניא, Detanya, we talk in a ברייתא. Braisa. אמר רבי מאיר,
Amar Rabbi Meir, said רב מאיר, Rav Meir, לא נחלקו רבי אליעזר
ורבי יהושע על מי שהיו לו שני תינוקות אחד למול בערב שבת
ואחד למול בשבת ושכח ומל של ערב שבת בשבת. lo necheliku Rabbi
Eliezer ve'Rabbi Yehoshua amisha hayu lo beis tinokos echad lamul be'erev shabbos
ve'echad lamul be'shabbos veshachach umal shel erev shabbos be'shabbos.
They did not disagree in the case- they actually they agreed in
the case of the Friday one that you did on שבת. Shabbos.
שהוא פטור, Shehu patur, that they both agree that you're exempt. Now,
so here's the difference. The first version says everybody agrees on the
Sunday one that you did on שבת Shabbos you're חייב chayav and
the debate is the Friday one on שבת. Shabbos. This says the
flip, not the flip but whatever, this says no, no, no, the
Friday one on שבת Shabbos everybody agrees you're exempt because you actually
wound up doing a מצוה. mitzvah. The debate is the Sunday one
that you did on שבת. Shabbos. Okay. על מה נחלקו? Alman necheliku?
What do they debate? על מי שהיו לו שני תינוקות אחד למול
לאחר שבת ואחד למול בשבת, Amisha hayu lo beis tinokos echad lamul
be'achar shabbos ve'echad lamul be'shabbos, one for Sunday and one for שבת.
Shabbos. ושכח ומל של לאחר שבת בשבת, Veshachach umal shel achar shabbos
be'shabbos, you accidentally did the Sunday one on שבת. Shabbos. שרבי אליעזר
מחייב חטאת, She'Rabbi Eliezer mechayev chatas, רבי אליעזר Rabbi Eliezer says you
bring a חטאת, chatas, ורבי יהושע פוטר, ve'Rabbi Yehoshua poter, רבי יהושע
Rabbi Yehoshua exempts you. ושניהם לא למדו אלא מעבודה כוכבים, Veshenehem lo
lamdu ela me'avodah kochavim, same point, we only learn it from עבודה
כוכבים. avodah kochavim. רבי אליעזר סבר כעבודה כוכבים, Rabbi Eliezer savar ke'avodah
kochavim, like עבודה זרה. avodah zarah. מה עבודה כוכבים אמר רחמנא לא
תעביד וכי עביד מחייב הכא נמי לא שנא. Mah avodah kochavim amar
rachmana lo sa'avid ve'chi avid mechayev hacha nami lo shna. עבודה זרה
Avodah zarah
the תורה Torah tells you you don't do it, if you do
it you're מחייב, mechayev, here too it doesn't matter. רבי יהושע, Rabbi
Yehoshua, רבי יהושע Rabbi Yehoshua said
no, התם לא טריד מצוה, hasam lo tarid mitzvah,
there you're not involved in a מצוה. mitzvah. הכא טריד מצוה, Hacha
tarid mitzvah, here you're involved in a מצוה, mitzvah, even though you
didn't wind up performing a מצוה mitzvah because what you wound up
doing was a Sunday מילה milah on שבת, Shabbos, so you didn't
succeed in doing a מצוה. mitzvah. Nevertheless, since it was in the
process of trying to do a מצוה mitzvah you are exempt. So
context meant though, right, in
other words you can't say like if I'm eating חזיר chazir while
taking a לולב lulav I'm exempt from eating...
Yeah, but it wasn't exactly the same act because when you had
the baby in front of you, it wasn't this baby that you
had a license to do a מצוה mitzvah for, you know, but
it was right, I mean it was obviously related, it was relating
to the מצוה mitzvah of מילה. milah. So anyway, so according to
this, meaning everybody agrees, according to either version, that it's better when
you wound up succeeding in doing the מצוה. mitzvah. The better case
is Friday done on שבת. Shabbos. Okay, the debate is, according to
one version, everybody says when it's the Sunday on שבת Shabbos you're
חייב, chayav, because that you didn't even do a מצוה. mitzvah. The
מחלוקת machlokes is if you actually succeeded in doing a מצוה, mitzvah,
that's where they debate. רבי יהושע Rebbi Yehoshua says you're exempt and
רבי אליעזר Rebbi Eliezer says you're חייב. chayav. The other version is
no, when you succeeded in doing the מצוה, mitzvah, the Friday-שבת Shabbos
case, then everybody says you're exempt. The whole debate is when you
didn't succeed but you were still involved in a מצוה, mitzvah, is
that enough to say that you are not חייב chayav a חטאת?
chatas? Okay, and that is the debate.
So let's take a look. תני רבי חייא. Tani Rebbi Chiya. תניא,
Tanya, we're
talking about a ברייתא. braisa. רבי חייא Rebbi Chiya taught a ברייתא,
braisa, אמר היה רבי מאיר, amar hayah Rebbi Meir, רבי מאיר Rebbi
Meir used to say, לא נחלקו רבי אליעזר ורבי יהושע על מי
שהיו לו שני תינוקות אחד למול בערב שבת ואחד למול בשבת, lo
nechelku Rebbi Eliezer ve-Rebbi Yehoshua al mi she-hayu lo shene tinokos echad
limol be-erev Shabbos ve-echad limol be-Shabbos, they did not argue in a
case where you had two infants, one for Friday and one for
שבת, Shabbos, ושכח ומל של ערב שבת בשבת שהוא חייב, ve-shachach u-mal
shel erev Shabbos be-Shabbos she-hu chayav, and you did the Friday one
on שבת Shabbos you're חייב. chayav. Now that's strange. There it says
everybody agrees the Friday one done on שבת Shabbos you're חייב, chayav,
even though you did a מצוה. mitzvah. על מה נחלקו, al mah
nechelku, what was the debate? על מי שהיו לו שני תינוקות אחד
למול לאחר שבת ואחד למול בשבת, al mi she-hayu lo shene tinokos
echad limol le-achar Shabbos ve-echad limol be-Shabbos, two infants, one for Sunday,
one for
שבת, Shabbos, ושכח ומל של אחר שבת בשבת
שרבי אליעזר מחייב חטאת ורבי יהושע פוטר. ve-shachach u-mal shel achar Shabbos
be-Shabbos she-Rebbi Eliezer mechayev chatas ve-Rebbi Yehoshua poter. רבי אליעזר Rebbi Eliezer
says you're חייב chayav and רבי יהושע Rebbi Yehoshua says you're exempt.
Now that's crazy. That's not just a disagreement where they argue, that's
reversing the order, that's reversing like which one is weightier. That says
if you did the Friday one on שבת, Shabbos, then everybody agrees
you're חייב, chayav, even though you did a מצוה. mitzvah. But there's,
but רבי יהושע Rebbi Yehoshua says you're exempt if you did the
Sunday one on שבת. Shabbos. Why should the Sunday one on שבת
Shabbos be better than the Friday one on שבת? Shabbos? So that's
what the גמרא's Gemara going to ask.
גמרא Gemara says השתא רבי יהושע סיפא דלא קעביד מצוה פוטר רישא
דקעביד מצוה מחייב? hashta Rebbi Yehoshua seifa de-lo ka-avid mitzvah poter reisha
de-ka-avid mitzvah mechayev? So אמרי דבי רבי ינאי, amri devei Rebbi Yannai,
they say in
the
house of רבי ינאי, Rebbi Yannai, רישא כגון שקדם ומל של שבת
בערב שבת. reisha kegon she-kodam u-mal shel Shabbos be-erev Shabbos. No, no,
no.
When we said in the first case that you did the Friday
one on שבת, Shabbos, that was the, what is a common scenario
to say you did the Friday one on שבת Shabbos is that
you mixed up the babies, right? So if you mixed up the
babies, you did the שבת Shabbos one on Friday and the Friday
one on שבת. Shabbos. So when שבת Shabbos rolls around, you no
longer have a license to violate שבת, Shabbos, right? Because the שבת
Shabbos one was already done yesterday. So that's why everybody agrees you're
חייב. chayav. It's true you wound up doing a מצוה, mitzvah, but
because you mixed up the babies, there's no license to violate שבת
Shabbos now. The שבת Shabbos one was already done yesterday. דלא ניתנה
שבת להידחות. de-lo nitnah Shabbos le-hidachos. שבת Shabbos
is no longer has a right to be overridden now because you
did the שבת Shabbos one yesterday. Now if when you mixed up
the Sunday and שבת Shabbos one in the same case of reversing
the baby, so fine, you did the Sunday one today on שבת.
Shabbos. The שבת Shabbos one hasn't yet been done. So because of
the שבת Shabbos one, you still have a license to violate שבת,
Shabbos, you just got confused which was which. סיפא ניתנה שבת להידחות.
seifa nitnah Shabbos le-hidachos. In the end case, you still have the
שבת Shabbos one around so you still have a right to override
שבת. Shabbos. That actually makes a lot of sense, that's the most
common scenario of this happening is you just got confused which baby
was which. So therefore we now have a different point. Yeah, but
it's not only the issue of whether you thought you were doing
a מצוה, mitzvah, but it was whether you were having a license
to be doing such a thing on שבת Shabbos itself. So therefore
there's two factors: one is what you, did you succeed in doing
a מצוה, mitzvah, were you involved in a מצוה, mitzvah, B, did
you succeed in doing a מצוה mitzvah even if not the מצוה
mitzvah that should have been done today? And B, which is what's
being pointed out here, do you actually have a license to be
violating שבת Shabbos to be doing what you were doing? And for
that he says the baby still has to be not yet נימול,
nimol, the שבת Shabbos baby. אמר ליה רב אשי לרב כהנא רישא
נמי ניתנה שבת להידחות לגבי תינוקות דעלמא. amar leh Rav Ashi le-Rav
Kahana reisha nami nitnah Shabbos le-hidachos legabe tinokos de-alma. So now this
is Joe's point. He says I don't get it. Even if you
mixed up the Friday and the שבת Shabbos one and you did
the שבת Shabbos one on Friday, I'm sure there's some other infant
around somewhere that could have a ברית מילה bris milah today. So
you do have a right in general to do ברית מילות bris
milahs today for eight-day-old babies. So why isn't that enough of giving
you a license? You think this baby in front of you, this
Friday baby, you think it's the שבת Shabbos baby, and it actually
is true that if it were a שבת Shabbos baby and there
are שבת Shabbos babies in the world that you would have a
right to override שבת. Shabbos. So why doesn't that give you enough
of a license? So the גמרא Gemara says להאי גברא מיהא לא
אישתרי. le-hai gavra miha lo ishtari. For you in this circumstance, you
the מוהל, mohel, you don't have a license. There's no babies around
right now in this town that you're being asked to do the
ברית מילה bris milah for that gives you that license. So the
fact that in theory, had I had an
eight day baby,
that
doesn't count.
Who we back it like? You know what, when there's a בית
המקדש Bais Hamikdash coming around and you have to worry about bringing
a חטאת, Chatas, I'll let you know who we back it like.
I don't remember how the רמב"ם. Rambam. Okay fine. Anyway, let's now
continue to the next משנה. Mishna. I just wanted to see one
thing here, whether it was... Yeah okay fine. All right, let's take
a look. Yes.
Why did they bring it from עבודה זרה? Avodah Zarah? I mean,
there are a million examples they could have brought that.
Yeah, because the case in the תורה Torah is... when it speaks
about doing... bringing a חטאת, Chatas, it's in שלח. Shelach. It says
וכי תשגו ולא תעשו את כל המצות האלה אשר צוה ה', v'chi
tishgu v'lo ta'asu eis kol hamitzvos ha'eileh asher tziva Hashem, I think,
hold on, let me pull you the פסוק. Pasuk. The case is
understood by חז"ל Chazal to be a case of... of עבודה זרה.
Avodah Zarah. Okay,
so it's very specifically here at the end of שלח Shelach it
says, וכי תשגו
ולא תעשו את כל המצות האלה,
v'chi tishgu
v'lo ta'asu eis kol hamitzvos ha'eileh, asher tziva
Hashem, then it says ונפש אחת תחטא בשגגה v'nefesh achas techeta b'shigagah
וכפר הכהן על הנפש החטאת בשגגה לפני ה'. v'chiper hacohen al hanefesh
hachoteis bishgagah lifnei Hashem. So
anyway... Yeah, because it says מכל המצות האלה. mikol hamitzvos ha'eileh. So
what's כנגד כל המצות? k'neged kol hamitzvos? It's you know, whatever. Although
the funny thing is that there is a special קרבן, Korban, it's
not your classic קרבן Korban
of עבודה זרה Avodah Zarah because עבודה זרה Avodah Zarah is an
עז ez and a normal קרבן Korban is like, you know, a
female is a כשבה kesevah or שעירה. se'irah.
But anyway, somehow it does serve as a model. Pretty funny also
because how much is it really learning from עבודה זרה? Avodah Zarah?
It's really just saying like, one says okay, with every case of
a sin, and the other says I think when you're doing a
מצוה Mitzvah it's different. But you know, it's not like there's so
much there that's being sort of derived. Okay, let's take a look
now at the next משנה.
Mishna. I can't imagine that such a case would happen. The parents
of the baby would know that he's not eight days old, right?
Others would know. That's an interesting case, although you could imagine in
a case which is like what we're about to see in the
next משנה Mishna that there were twins and you one was born
and so you got mixed up which was first and which was
second. Right?
But somebody would know, the mother.
Yeah, but you know, in the whole confusion or whatever, it's possible.
You could definitely see... I can see a possible scenario. Anyway, let's
take a look because that's the next משנה. Mishna. קטן נימול לשמונה
לתשעה לעשרה לאחד עשר לשנים עשר. Katan nimal lishmonah, l'tishah, l'asarah, l'achad
asar, l'shneim asar. Very interesting because פורים Purim is right around the
corner. It's like the משנה Mishna in the beginning of
מגילה. Megillah. מגילה נקראת Megillah nikreis בי"ג בי"ד בי"ב בי"א. b'yud gimmel,
b'yud daled, b'yud beis, b'yud aleph. Okay, so an infant can have
a ברית מילה Bris Milah on the eighth day, ninth, tenth, eleventh,
or twelfth. לא פחות ולא יותר. Lo fachos v'lo yoseir. Not less
and not more. Now obviously it could be more if it's delayed,
but it means that under normal circumstances it should not be later
than the twelfth. Certain circumstances would warrant a twelfth and otherwise it
would be considered late. כיצד? Keitzad? What's an example? כדרכו לשמונה. K'darko
lishmonah. Normal case is eighth day. נולד לבין השמשות. Nolad l'vein hashmashos.
If it's בין השמשות bein hashmashos on any... let's say between a
Monday and a Tuesday. נימול לתשעה. Nimal l'tesha. Then it's nine. I
mean nine if you count from the Monday. So it's בין השמשות
bein hashmashos between Monday and Tuesday, it's going to be nine days
from Monday because it might have been a Tuesday baby and then
it should be eight days from Tuesday. So in that case it's
going to be nine days from Monday. Now, בין השמשות ערב שבת,
Bein hashmashos erev Shabbat, let's say it's בין השמשות bein hashmashos between
Friday and שבת. Shabbos. So you can't do it next Friday because
maybe it's a שבת Shabbos baby. You can't do it next שבת
Shabbos because maybe it's a Friday baby and you can't override שבת
Shabbos for a ninth day ברית מילה. Bris Milah. So what do
you do? You wind up doing it on נימול לעשרה nimal l'asarah
on Sunday, which is the tenth day counting from Friday. Now, יום
טוב לאחר שבת, Yom Tov l'achar Shabbat, let's say it's born between
Friday and שבת Shabbos but it is the following week has a
יום טוב Yom Tov on Sunday. So you can't do it on
Sunday either because it's not the eighth day and therefore you can't
do a יום טוב Yom Tov ברית Bris on not the eighth
day. So נימול לאחד עשר, nimal l'achad asar, you'll do it on
Monday. שני ימים של ראש השנה, Shenei yamim shel Rosh Hashanah, let's
say the following week actually Sunday-Monday is ראש השנה. Rosh Hashanah. Okay,
which we can't have in our calendar.
I know, okay, anyway, in that case, so you can't do it
on שבת, Shabbos, maybe it was a Friday baby. You
can't do it on Friday maybe it was a שבת Shabbos baby.
You can't do it on Sunday-Monday because it was either Friday or
שבת Shabbos baby and therefore it's not בזמנו bizmano and it doesn't
override יום טוב. Yom Tov. So in that case, נימול לשנים עשר.
nimal lishneim asar. It's going to be on Tuesday on the twelfth
day counting from Friday.
If you have to שחט shecht an animal for food, right, you
still can't...
You cannot do... that was an earlier סוגיא Sugya that you cannot
do a ברית מילה Bris Milah שלא בזמנו. shelo bizmano. It's not
לצורך היום. l'tzorech hayom. קטן החולה... Katan hacholeh... קטן החולה אין מלין
אותו עד שיבריא. Katan hacholeh ain molin oso ad sheyeivarei. If the
infant is sick, then you don't do the ברית מילה Bris Milah
until he gets better. That obviously is a reason to postpone the
ברית מילה Bris Milah because of health concerns.
Okay. So now by the way, so if it's case of twins,
this actually was in my this this was true about me. My
my I'm a twin, my twin brother and I were born on
Friday which was ראש השנה Rosh Hashanah and שבת שובה. Shabbos Shuva.
So I was so he was born בין השמשות, bein hashmashos, he
was first, and I was born on שבת. Shabbos. So had we
had a ברית מילה בזמנו, Bris Milah bizmano, which we didn't because
we were a month premature, so we had the ברית מילה Bris
Milah and the פדיון הבן pidyon haben the same day. But anyway,
had we had the ברית מילה בזמנו, Bris Milah bizmano, I would
have been on יום כיפור Yom Kippur and he would have been
on Sunday. So that's like a good trick question. How can you
have twins where the older one has the ברית מילה Bris Milah
the day after the younger one? So there you go, but it
didn't happen to me. Okay. Anyway, so אמר שמואל, Amar Shmuel,
חלצתו חמה, chaltzaso chamah, so
we focus on the case of getting sick. If he basically has
been like,
you know, the heat has removed from him, so he had a
fever and now he
has recovered, the fever broke. נותנים לו כל שבעה להבראתו. nosnin lo
kol shiva l'havraso. You give him a week to make sure he's
fully healthy, you don't rush to do the ברית מילה Bris Milah
the next day. איבעיא
להו, ibaya lehu, they raised the question: מי בעינן מעת לעת? mi
bainenan me'es l'es? When you say you give him a week, is
it a week from the time the fever broke or is it
just into the, you know, seven, is it like halakhic days? Beginning
the after, beginning into the seventh day. תא שמע, ta shma, come
and hear, דתני לודא, d'tani Luda, Luda is the name of some
sage taught, יום הבראתו כיום הולדתו. yom havraso k'yom hivaldo. The day
that he gets healed, the day the fever breaks is like his
day of birth. And the same way when he gets born you
give him the ברית מילה Bris Milah on the eighth day, the
day that the fever breaks you give him the ברית מילה Bris
Milah the eighth day from that day. So the גמרא Gemara says,
מאי לאו, mai lav, yeah but seven days is seven days from
that day is the eighth day, right? Okay. So מאי לאו, mai
lav, it depends if you count the first day as day one,
right? Okay. מאי לאו, mai lav, מה יום הולדתו לא בעינן מעת
לעת, ma yom hivaldo lo bainenan me'es l'es, don't we say the
same way when he's born, the ברית מילה Bris Milah doesn't have
to be seven full days, right? It's just the beginning of the
eighth day, it doesn't need seven twenty-four hour, hour, seven times twenty-four
hours. מה יום הולדתו לא בעינן מעת לעת אף יום הבראתו לא
בעינן מעת לעת. ma yom hivaldo lo bainenan me'es l'es af yom
havraso lo bainenan me'es l'es. So the day when he gets better,
you do it, on the eighth day from the day he gets
better, it doesn't have to be seven twenty-four hour days. לא, lo,
no, not necessarily. עדיף יום הבראתו מיום הולדתו. adif yom havraso miyom
hivaldo. Maybe it's more. דאילו יום הולדתו לא בעינן מעת לעת, d'ilu
yom hivaldo lo bainenan me'es l'es, because from eighth day from birth,
it's not מעת לעת, me'es l'es, it's just whatever the eighth day
is. He could be born on the end of Sunday right before
sunset and you give him the ברית bris first thing Sunday morning.
ואילו יום הבראתו בעינן מעת לעת, v'ilu yom havraso bainenan me'es l'es,
but the day he gets better maybe you need literally because anyway
it's about health, it's not like a halakhic point, so maybe you
need seven full days. Now by the way according to this the
only concern of the גמרא Gemara is the issue of how long
is it going to take him to get better. You wait till
he's better to do the ברית מילה. Bris Milah. There are some
cases where because regardless of health issues, if the baby is sick,
we don't start counting the eight days from the day that he's
born during the period he's sick. And other times you do start
counting. Is that clear what I'm talking about? You know, let's say
the baby is born with jaundice, right? And then it clears up.
Do you do the ברית מילה Bris Milah eight days from the
day he's born or do you wait from, meaning the גמרא Gemara
here seems to be just a pure health concern. Let's say we've
addressed health concerns, you ask the doctor, totally fine, yeah there was
a period we thought he wasn't going to be able to because
of jaundice but really he's totally fine you could do the ברית
מילה Bris Milah tomorrow. Do we do the ברית מילה Bris Milah
then or is there some idea that no, during the period when
he's sick and the ברית מילה Bris Milah wasn't possible, don't count
towards the eight days from the day that he's born? There actually
are some times that we say that, although you would not know
that from this גמרא. Gemara. I understand, I understand, it's not there
you would not know that from this גמרא. Gemara. This גמרא Gemara
sounds like it's purely a health issue. There are some times we
do say that, just wanted to let you know, but yes, it's
not in this גמרא. Gemara.
Okay, now wrapping up talking about the actual act of the ברית
מילה, Bris Milah, this was referred to earlier when it talks about
being able to go back and finish it on שבת. Shabbos. אלו
הן ציצין המעכבין. Eilu hein tzitzin ham'akvin. The following are the little
pieces of skin that prevent the ברית מילה Bris Milah from being
כשר kosher if you didn't remove them. את המילה בשר החופה את
רוב העטרה. Es hamilah basar hachofeh es rov ha'atarah. If there's flesh
that covers the majority of the corona, right, the raised area at
the top. ואינו אוכל בתרומה. V'eino ochel bitrumah. Now that makes him
considered an ערל, arel, so not only is it like he's not
יוצא yotzei the ברית מילה, Bris Milah, if he's a כהן Kohen
he can't eat תרומה. terumah. It says כל ערל לא יאכל בו.
kol arel lo yochal bo. It's not a question of whether it's
your fault or not your fault. The גמרא Gemara says it even
applies to somebody who's a hemophiliac and can't have a ברית מילה.
Bris Milah. So anyway, even if there's just a little, these pieces
of skin, he's still an ערל arel and he can't eat תרומה.
terumah. ואם היה בעל בשר, V'im hayah ba'al basar, now let's say
he was somebody that was very heavy, weighty, fat, so מתקנו מפני
מראית העין. misakno mipnei maris ha'ayin. Even if the ברית מילה Bris
Milah is done correctly. exactly you do so you you make it
so that it because of concerns of appearances. Now this is quite
fascinating, like who's looking at you? Now of course they did have
a whole bathhouse culture, public bathhouses. So apparently if somebody is very
fat, there would be a concern that the extra fleshy sort of
flesh would go would cover up part of the corona and it
would look like a foreskin. So even if actually the ברית מילה
brit milah was done
fully, the, you know, they would do something extra, I mean functionally
you would cut away extra skin in that area or something, I
don't know exactly even know, but so that it should not look
like you had not done a ברית מילה. brit milah. Now that
could also be, I don't know, not on שבת. Shabbat.
It says מעכבי את המילה me-akvei et ha-milah and no,
no, no, we're beyond מעכבי את המילה. me-akvei et ha-milah. Separate point.
Now what's also interesting though is again, that that we would sort
of say you do this surgical thing because somebody might be looking
in the bathhouse, it's an interesting application of מראית העין. marit ha-ayin.
But one also, it is also a time where there's a where
because of, you know, the influence of Hellenistic culture, a lot of
Jews are actually not having a ברית מילה brit milah or trying
to reverse their ברית מילה, brit milah, so you could understand why
we would really try to advise that type of a thing, even
though we're really sort of saying do some additional surgical procedure. Okay,
now מל ולא פרע את המילה כאילו לא מל. mal velo para
et ha-milah ke-ilu lo mal. If you did a ברית מילה brit
milah and you did not do the פריעה, periah, which is the
tearing away of the membrane underneath, then it's like you did not
do the ברית מילה. brit milah. And by the way, it is
pointed out that the פריעה periah also makes it almost impossible, there
was a surgery that they did to reverse the מילה milah and
that was almost impossible to be done after if a פריעה periah
was done. So that's also interesting, but the גמרא Gemara understands that
the פריעה periah is part of the הלכה למשה מסיני halachah le-Moshe
mi-Sinai of ברית מילה brit milah and that you could even do
it on שבת, Shabbat,
it overrides
it overrides שבת. Shabbat. So, let's take a look at the גמרא.
Gemara. אמר רבי אבין, amar Rabbi Avin, so that was the last
משנה, Mishnah, now we'll do the last גמרא Gemara about ברית מילה.
brit milah. אמר רבי אבין אמר רבי ירמיה בר אבא אמר רב
בשר החופה את רוב גובה של עטרה. amar Rabbi Avin amar Rabbi
Yirmiyah bar Abba amar Rav basar ha-chofeh et rov govah shel ha-atarah.
We do not mean the way רש"י Rashi reads this, when we
say that it prevents it, when it's רוב העטרה, rov ha-atarah, the
majority, we don't mean that it covers the majority of the circumference
of the עטרה, atarah, which is what you would have thought. What
we're saying is that no, what it means is that it covers
the majority of the height of the עטרה atarah even if only
in one location. So even one little piece of skin in one
location that covers the height of the corona, that would be enough
to say that it is not good, so all the skin has
to be removed from the entire circumference. Okay, ואם היה בעל בשר,
ve-im haya ba'al basar, and if he's fleshy, so אמר שמואל קטן
המשורבב בבשר. amar Shmuel katan ha-meshorbav bi-vasar. If you have an infant
that is very like layered in fat, which is interesting because I
think there's other גמרות Gemaras about how שמואל Shmuel was very heavy.
Anyway, רואין אותו. ro'in oto. You inspect him. כל זמן שמתקשה ונראה
מהול. kol zeman she-mitkasheh ve-nir'eh mahul. If when he has an erection,
I mean even infants can get an erection, and I'm sure you
can like stimulate it too. Anyway, so if when he gets an
erection ונראה מהול, ve-nir'eh mahul, then, you know, then it does appear
that he's circumcised because then the flesh stretches, אינו צריך למול, eino
tzarich lamul, then you do not have to do any extra surgery
to make it look better. ואם לאו, ve-im lav, but if he
does not even in that case צריך למול, tzarich lamul, you have
to. Which is again quite interesting because if it's a concern of
מראית העין, marit ha-ayin, then who's looking when you have an erection?
It's one thing in the bathhouse, but you know, so it's quite
fascinating.
But the parents are looking when they change his diaper.
I understand, but we're not concerned about the מראית העין marit ha-ayin
of the parents. במתניתא תנא, ve-matnita tana, in the ברייתא Baraita we
taught: רבן גמליאל אומר קטן המשורבב בבשר רואין אותו. Rabban Gamliel omer
katan ha-meshorbav bi-vasar ro'in oto. Same thing that שמואל Shmuel taught, this
is a ברייתא. Baraita. כל זמן שמתקשה ואינו נראה מהול צריך למול.
kol zeman she-mitkasheh ve-eino nir'eh mahul tzarich lamul. Every time that he
has an erection and he appears non-circumcised, then you have to go
ahead and do, you know, do something, you know, do something more.
ואם לאו, ve-im lav, if that's not the case, אינו צריך למול,
eino tzarich lamul, you do not have to. So now it sounds
like the same thing, but the difference was שמואל Shmuel says if
he appears circumcised, you're okay. The ברייתא Baraita says if he appears
uncircumcised, you've got a problem. So מאי בינייהו? mai beinaihu? What difference
is there between how you articulate it? איכא בינייהו נראה ואינו נראה.
ika beinaihu nir'eh ve-eino nir'eh. It sort of somewhat looks like it's
circumcised, somewhat not. So if you say if it appears circumcised, you're
good, that means that you have to satisfy the criteria of looking
circumcised, that means you have to be totally look okay. If you
say if it looks uncircumcised, you're no good, well it doesn't look
uncircumcised, he's somewhere in this middle zone. Right? There's a gap between
saying, you know, A, you know, there's the space between. Here's circumcised,
here's not circumcised. There's a space in between where it's somewhat a
little, you know, a little gray. So שמואל Shmuel says you have
to look circumcised to be okay, that's a higher standard than the
ברייתא Baraita which says if it's not looks not circumcised then you
have to do something. All right, מל ולא פרע. mal velo para.
Now we get onto the פריעה, periah, although the really the גמרא
Gemara doesn't have anything to say at this stage about the פריעה
periah and it turns to wrapping up the discussion of ברית מילה
brit milah by talking about the ברכות. brachot. Interestingly, the idea of
ברכות brachot is not mentioned in the משניות, Mishnayot, they come from
the תוספתא, Tosefta, comes from a ברייתא. Baraita. So let's take a
look. המל אומר, ha-mal omer, the person doing the ברית מילה, brit
milah, the מוהל mohel says: אשר קדשנו. asher kiddeshanu. המל hamal אומר,
omer, the person doing the ברית מילה, brit milah, the מוהל mohel
says, אשר קדשנו במצותיו וצונו על המילה. asher kiddishanu bemitzvotav vetzivanu al
hamila. אבי הבן avi haben אומר, omer, אשר קדשנו במצותיו וצונו להכניסו
בבריתו של אברהם אבינו, asher kiddishanu bemitzvotav vetzivanu lehachniso bivrito shel avraham
avinu, that you commanded us to bring us into the ברית brit
of אברהם אבינו avraham avinu because although we say the מצוה mitzvah
of מילה mila is on the father,
most logically what that means is that the father has to see
to it that he gets the ברית מילה, brit milah, not that
the father has to personally do the ברית מילה. brit milah. There
are some fathers that now sort of want to do it themselves
or or that they hand over the scalpel to the מוהל mohel
and make him a שליח, shaliach, but the simple understanding is not
that it's his personal מצוה mitzvah to do it, it's his personal
מצוה mitzvah to see that it gets done. So the מוהל mohel
who's doing it says אשר קדשנו במצותיו וצונו על המילה, asher kiddishanu
bemitzvotav vetzivanu al hamila, he's the one doing the act. The father
says my obligation was not to do it, but להכניסו בבריתו של
אברהם אבינו lehachniso bivrito shel avraham avinu to see that he gets
brought into the covenant of אברהם אבינו. avraham avinu. So number one,
it reflects more what the father's obligation is, and number two, it
frames it. It's not just a מצוה mitzvah like taking the לולב,
lulav, there's larger implications here. It's about entering into the ברית. brit.
העומדים שם אומרים ha'omedim sham omrim and those that are standing around
say, כשם שנכנס לברית כן יכנס לתורה ולחופה ולמעשים טובים. keshem shenichnas
labrit ken yichanes letorah ulechupa ulema'asim tovim. The same way he entered
into the ברית brit he should enter into תורה, torah, חופה, chupa,
and מעשים טובים. ma'asim tovim. Now, this is actually not the correct
גרסא girsa of the גמרא. gemara. If you look at the ב"ח,
Bach, the ב"ח Bach says, and there's no question this is the
original
גרסא, girsa, אות א ot alef on the left hand column, כשם
שהכנסתו לברית כן תכניסהו לתורה ולחופה ולמעשים טובים. keshem shehichnasto labrit ken
tachniseyhu letorah ulechupa ulema'asim tovim. Because the father said, "You commanded me
להכניסו lehachniso that I should bring him into the ברית brit of
אברהם אבינו." avraham avinu. And the people say, "כשם שהכנסתו, keshem shehichnasto,
the same way you brought him into the ברית brit of אברהם
אבינו, avraham avinu, כן תכניסהו ken tachniseyhu you should bring him in
לתורה ולחופה ולמעשים טובים." letorah ulechupa ulema'asim tovim. Now that also connects
to the משנה mishna in קידושין Kiddushin that says it's the father's
obligation to do what? To give his son a ברית מילה, brit
milah, to marry him, and to teach him a trade. So you
should be מכניס machnis him, as you were מכניס machnis him לברית
labrit you should be מכניס machnis
him לחופה, lechupa, לתורה—I'm letorah sorry—to teach him תורה, torah, so you
have to get him married, you have to teach him תורה, torah,
and מעשים טובים, ma'asim tovim, a productive life, you have to give
him a trade. Exactly what the משנה mishna in
קידושין Kiddushin says what the father's obligations are and it exactly parallels
the ברכה beracha of the father. So why do we say כשם
שנכנס? keshem shenichnas? This actually was an Ashkenazic change of the נוסח
nusach because there were so many births where the father was dead,
where due to
the types of challenges that were in the Middle Ages in Ashkenazi
society, very often the father would not be around. Therefore, if there's
no—I think
personally, I don't know enough about the specifics, I know that it's
Ashkenazic, it was specifically an Ashkenazic case and not a Sefardic case.
In ספרדים, Sefardim, so I imagine it had to do with the
persecution and
everything is changed because instead of the baby, it focuses on the
baby.
So here was the thing: he should get married. I understand, the
meaning does change. But here I want to make a point, the
first step would have been if the father isn't around, you can't
say כשם שהכנסתו, keshem shehichnasto, then you say כשם שנכנס. keshem shenichnas.
But then not to highlight the cases where the father was dead
as opposed to the cases where the father was
alive, they switched it so that for all kids they would say
כשם שנכנס keshem shenichnas even when the father was alive. It does
change the emphasis, the emphasis is completely different.
And the mother of course is if the father's not
there, it's not the mother's obligation. That's true.
She doesn't get any ברכה beracha here because if the father is
getting a ברכה beracha to be זוכה zocheh to see this, then
the
mother would not be included.
If it's the baby getting the ברכה, beracha, then that's a whole
different thing.
I understand. It might also be I have to find out more
about the historical facts that this is
about. First of all it could also have been due to
conversion, that maybe sometimes fathers—we have stories definitely about mothers converting out,
it could be cases where the fathers converting out as well. But
here's the other case I know that also points to similar historical
realities, although I don't know enough about the specifics, is this whole
issue about marrying under-aged daughters which
תוספות Tosafot speaks about how this was a קידושי קטנה, kidushei ketana,
how the גמרא gemara sort of pushes back against this because the
girl should have a say and all this type of thing. Anyway,
תוספות Tosafot talks about how in the period of medieval Ashkenaz it
was more prevalent to do it. The reason you do it is
because you're not sure you're going to be around to provide for
your daughter and you want to make sure that that is taken
care of. So the idea about whether, how long would generally be
lifespan of people. About how in the period of medieval אשכנז, Ashkenaz,
it was more prevalent to do it. Now the reason you do
it is because you're not sure you're going to be around to
provide for your daughter, and you want to make sure that that
is taken care of. So the idea about whether how long would
you know what generally would be lifespan of people and whether it
was specifically due to persecution or other types of issues, but that
was a concern about.
Don't the תוספות Tosafot say because now you have the money to
do it? You might not have the money at other times.
That could be, I think though they also say
and then no one will marry her.
That's true, but I
also that's what תוספות Tosafot says, I've come in there now.
Oh really? Okay. From what I remember there's also discussion about whether
about whether you'll be around. But anyway, it definitely was true. Again,
I don't know the full historical background, but in אשכנז Ashkenaz it
was a concern about cases where the father wasn't around, and therefore
you would take כסף שנכנס Kesef Shenichnas and once you said it
for those cases you wound up saying it for all cases. Most
people are completely unaware of that, right? And they it's exactly like
רבקה, Rifka, they totally assume it's a ברכה Beracha for the infant
where really originally it's a ברכה Beracha for the father.
It's a true question. Now that this isn't as much a concern
is there no push to like, you know, make it at or
and then the other question is maybe the גמרא Gemara just doesn't
want to go over here, what about the שהחיינו Shehecheyanu part? Are
they not doing that because it's not really part of the actual
ברית Brit part?
Yeah, the גמרא Gemara is not discussing the שהחיינו. Shehecheyanu. If the
ספרדים Sfaradim make the שהחיינו, Shehecheyanu, אשכנזים Ashkenazim do not, right? So
anyway, I don't want to discuss that
right now because the fact that it's omitted here doesn't prove one
way or the other.
Right, because it's focusing, although it's interesting you might have said because
it's not just focusing, I mean it's focusing on the whole ceremony
not only on the ברוך אתה, Baruch Atah, so maybe it is
somewhat significant. Yeah, it's a good point, it's a good point, yeah.
All right, so now let's see. The גמרא Gemara continues ומברך אומר.
U'mevarech omer. Now the blesser says. Who's this מברך, Mevarech, right? So
it sounds like you already had this institution that you had to
somebody other than, you know, the other than the מוהל Mohel and
the father, the idea maybe like the rabbi although it doesn't call
him the rabbi, but somebody there who's assigned the role to give
this special ברכה. Beracha. Okay, and here's the ברכה Beracha he says:
אשר קידש ידיד מבטן, Asher kiddash yedid mibeten, you sanctified the beloved
one in the womb, חוק בשארו שם, Chok bish'eiro sam, you placed
a, you know, a sign on his flesh, וצאצאיו חתם באות ברית
קודש, V'tse'etsa'av chatam be'ot berit kodesh, and his future progeny you have
sealed with the sign of the holy covenant. על כן, Al ken,
therefore בשכר זאת, Bischar zot, in the merit of this, אל חי
חלקנו, El chai chelkenu, God who has our the living God who
is our portion, צוה Tsaveh or here's an interesting question about the
גרסא, Girsa, is it צוה Tsaveh command or is it if you
look at the side the יעבץ Ya'avetz רב יעקב עמדן Rabbi Yaakov
Emden has the גרסא Girsa ציווה, Tsivah, You have commanded. So are
we asking God to command or are we saying God You have
commanded להציל ידידות שארנו משחת, Lehatsil yedidut she'erenu mishachat, to save our
beloved, our you know our beloved ones from destruction, למען בריתו אשר
שם בשארנו Lema'an brito asher sam bish'erenu because of the covenant that
has been placed in our flesh. ברוך אתה השם כורת הברית, Baruch
Atah Hashem koreit haberit, God who has sealed the covenant. Now this
is quite a fascinating ברכה Beracha if you think about it because
what is this? All of a sudden the ברית מילה Brit Milah
is to save kids from, you know, from destruction. Is this like
reflecting a concern of infant mortality and trying to see the ברית
מילה Brit Milah as some type of a divine sign that protects
them from infant death? That's certainly what it sounds like. But it's
very strange, like on the one hand the beginning is so powerful
about how, you know, this is going back to the sense of
it's the covenant and it goes all the way back to אברהם,
Avraham, יצחק, Yitzchak, and יעקב, Yaakov, and it's the covenant we carry
in our flesh for our future generations וצאצאיו חתם באות ברית קודש.
V'tse'etsa'av chatam be'ot berit kodesh. But the end of it, but the
end of it, על כן ציווה להציל ידידות שארנו Al ken tsivah
lehatsil yedidut she'erenu is a pretty interesting. If you look at רש"י,
Rashi, רש"י Rashi says משחת, Mishachat, רש"י Rashi says מגיהנום דכתיב גם
את בדם בריתך שלחתי אסיריך מבור אין מים בו. Migehennom dichtiv gam
at bedam britech shilachti asirayich mibor ein mayim bo. So saving us
from destruction does not mean protecting like from infant mortality, at least
according to רש"י, Rashi, it's more consistent with the more sort of
if you would religious meaning of the ברית, Brit, that because of
this we it, you know, it sort of gives us our Jewish
identity and it saves us from גיהנום. Gehennom. Again, this idea that
the ברית מילה Brit Milah saves from גיהנום Gehennom is something very
prevalent in the Middle Ages, not so much discussed really in the
גמרא, Gemara, but that's how רש"י Rashi reads it. But again, it
is quite fascinating, this end part of this ברכה Beracha that moves
to this idea of the ברית Brit as protective, not so much
just for the sense of the ברית Brit itself. Okay.
We skipped
over
the בורא פרי הגפן Borei pri hagafen because that's not mentioned here.
Yeah, the בורא פרי הגפן, Borei pri hagafen, בורא פרי הגפן Borei
pri hagafen occurs in the גמרא Gemara only for, you know, it
gets only for קידוש Kiddush basically and הבדלה, Havdalah, it gets extended
post the גמרא Gemara to all these other sort of life cycle
ritual ברכות. Berachot. So קידושין, Kiddushin, שבע ברכות, Sheva berachot, in
the גמרא Gemara never calls it שבע ברכות Sheva berachot because in
the גמרא Gemara it's six ברכות, Berachot, it only gets seven when
you add this, ברית מילה, Brit Milah, all of this the בורא
פרי הגפן Borei pri hagafen gets added afterwards. It's not in the
גמרא. Gemara. That's clear. Okay and Michael is also correct to raise
the שהחיינו Shehecheyanu question which isn't mentioned here and is a debate
of ספרדים Sfaradim and אשכנזים. Ashkenazim.
And how do little girls get saved?
Yeah, exactly, exactly. All of this heavy weight on the sense of
the ברית Brit for the boy, right, raises the whole question about
the whole issue of girls, absolutely. Okay, now I want to read
till the end and then I want to go back and discuss
a point that תוספות Tosafot raises about all of this. המל
את הגרים אומר, Hamal et hagerim omer, the one who makes the
ברכה Beracha on גרים Gerim who does מילה Milah on גרים Gerim
says. ברוך אתה ה' אלוקינו מלך העולם אשר קדשנו במצוותיו וצונו על
המילה. Baruch Ata Hashem Elokeinu Melech Haolam asher kideshanu bemitzvotav vetzivanu al
hamila. Same thing, you're just doing the act of מילה, mila, על
המילה, al hamila, you don't give it any broader framing or significance.
והמברך אומר vehamavarech omer and the מברך, mevarech, now who's the מברך?
mevarech? It's not the father, there's no, it's not about a father.
I mean, even if it's a case about like גרות קטן, geirus
katan, he's not presumably, it's interesting, although you know he doesn't seem
to have a particular role. Who's the מברך? mevarech? Some person that's
assigned to make this ברכה. bracha. אשר קדשנו במצוותיו וצונו למול את
הגרים ולהטיף מהם דם ברית. asher kideshanu bemitzvotav vetzivanu lamol et hagerim
ulehatif mehem dam brit. Okay, so he is the one that makes
this ברכה bracha that gives it like this significance, the same way
the other one made it, you know, about
that, to give... להטיף מהם דם ברית lehatif mehem dam brit because
most of the time, not most, but very often it would just
be the הטפת דם ברית, hatafat dam brit, not actually a מילה.
mila. שאילמלא דם ברית she'ilmalei dam brit were it not for the
blood of the covenant, לא נתקיימו שמים וארץ lo nitkaymu shamayim va'aretz
שנאמר אם לא בריתי יומם ולילה חוקות שמים וארץ לא שמתי. shenemar
im lo briti yomam valaila chukot shamayim va'aretz lo samti. If it
were not for my covenant, I would not have made the, you
know, the laws of heaven and earth, sort of
the laws of nature, the laws of heaven and earth. ברוך אתה
ה' כורת הברית. Baruch Ata Hashem koret habrit. Now what's interesting here
though is the דם ברית dam brit gets repeated. שאילמלא דם ברית,
she'ilmalei dam brit, not שאילמלא ברית, she'ilmalei brit, although the פסוק pasuk
only refers to אם לא בריתי. im lo briti. So again the
raising of the emphasis of the blood as part of the ritual,
you see here, you know, you can see where that gets encouraged
or reflected by this ברכה. bracha. And it is interesting as well
that, you know, the ברכה bracha of, although it says למול את
הגרים, lamol et hagerim, you know, it talks about the significance of
ברית, brit, not in...
I find this a little bit, I don't know if I'd say
troubling or curious, because you would have expected the ברכה bracha that's
giving the significance of גרים gerim to talk about how the גר
ger is being brought into the ברית של אברהם אבינו. brit shel
Avraham Avinu. Okay, so maybe it should say אשר קדשנו במצוותיו וצונו
להכניסו בבריתו, asher kideshanu bemitzvotav vetzivanu lehachniso bivrito, but if you're going
to talk about
שאילמלא, she'ilmalei, you know, whatever, you're just going to step back and
sort of talk about the significance. You could talk about what it
means to bring someone into the ברית של אברהם אבינו. brit shel
Avraham Avinu. And instead it's more generic of the significance of ברית
מילה, brit mila, just speaking generically. Okay, so that's a little strange
again because you would have expected something more specific about what the
ברית מילה brit mila means for the גר. ger. Okay, המל את
העבדים, hamal et ha'avadim, if you do a מילה mila on עבדים,
avadim, which you would do, אומר אשר קדשנו במצוותיו וצונו על המילה.
omer asher kideshanu bemitzvotav vetzivanu al hamila. והמברך אומר אשר קדשנו במצוותיו
וצונו למול את העבדים ולהטיף מהם דם ברית שאילמלא דם ברית חוקות
שמים וארץ לא נתקיימו שנאמר אם לא בריתי יומם ולילה חוקות שמים
וארץ לא שמתי ברוך אתה ה' כורת הברית. vehamavarech omer asher kideshanu
bemitzvotav vetzivanu lamol et ha'avadim ulehatif mehem dam brit she'ilmalei dam brit
chukot shamayim va'aretz lo nitkaymu shenemar im lo briti yomam valaila chukot
shamayim va'aretz lo samti Baruch Ata Hashem koret habrit. The exact same.
But again it is interesting because, yeah, no distinction between now, an
עבד eved was a quasi-גר ger in the sense that, you know,
he didn't have a say in the matter but he had partial
חיוב מצוות, chiyuv mitzvos, which does raise interesting questions of whether you
look at the ברית מילה brit mila for עבדים avadim the same
way you look at it for גר. ger. To what degree is
he entering into
the covenant? In the end for both of them, the ברכה bracha
is, right? מילה mila is just the act of cutting. ברית brit
is the larger significance of the ברית, brit, right? And so both
by the עבד eved and the גר ger you do in the
end say, but although you don't emphasize coming into the ברית של
אברהם, brit shel Avraham, you do say כורת הברית. koret habrit. In
the end you do say God makes the covenant, so you're acknowledging
that it's bringing them into the covenant, and it's interesting that you're
acknowledging that by the עבד eved as well. But of course then
it's a little bit disturbing because you would have wanted there to
have been a greater acknowledgement of that, some distinction between the גר
ger and the עבד eved in that regard. Okay, so very interesting
about how those cases are handled. Now I do want to say
something about these other ברכות. brachos.
One... what about if the ברית brit is on an adult Jewish
male?
Then you still say, you still certainly say the ברכה bracha of,
you know, על המילה. al hamila. Oh, it's interesting. Would you say
this like ברכה bracha of, you know, אשר להכניסו? asher lehachniso? Yeah,
yeah. The father presumably, once he's an adult, would not say להכניסו.
lehachniso. The question is... and it's interesting, because you're right, why in
theory don't you make a similar ברכה bracha to, you know, to
like the end of על המילה, al hamila, I mean... למול, lamol,
you know, whatever, to give greater weight to the significance, right? To
frame the significance of it. It's true, maybe they just were never
מתקן metaken that ברכה bracha because it was a rare case, you
know, so they never... so they didn't have an official ברכה bracha
for that case that's specific for that, but as far as, you
know, I, you know, there is... I don't know if anybody ever...
למעשה lema'aseh we don't do a... we don't make a parallel ברכה.
bracha. We, you know, in the case of an adult male that
parallels these ברכות brachos at the end.
You
just say על המילה, al hamila, you know.
But it's an interesting point because, you know, these adult males get
a ברכה, bracha, why shouldn't an adult Jewish male get a ברכה
bracha as well? It's a good point. I would have to look
if there's some discussion around that. Now I do want to say
that תוספות Tosafos has a problem in terms of, or raises an
issue in terms of the order, because the first ברכה, bracha, the
ברכה bracha about להכניסו בבריתו של אברהם אבינו, lehachniso bivrito shel Avraham
Avinu, he says the ל lamed normally refers to the future. So
therefore the question is you should make it before the מילה. mila.
להכניסו lehachniso means you're about to do it. So he actually says
that one... of the בעלי התוספות, baalei hatosfos, you know, one of
who was it he says רבינו שמואל, rabbeinu shmuel,
says that you actually should say להכניסו lehachniso before you say על
המילה. al hamilah. So you should say it before. That is of
course is not our approach. Our approach is, and the תוספות tosfos
makes it clear that that's changing the גרסא. girsa. Our approach is
that the מוהל mohel makes the ברכה, bracha, the מוהל mohel does
the מילה, milah, after the מוהל mohel does the ברית bris so
you say להכניסו. lehachniso. So,
but and even though ל li means normally implies you're about to
do it, it could also mean that you have done it, and
it's not really a problem. But the interesting question also here is,
you know, why don't we say כל מצות מברך עליהם עובר לעשייתן?
kol mitzvos mevorach aleihem over l'asiyasos? Right? Why doesn't the father have
to say להכניסו lehachniso before he actually does the מילה? milah? And
the point is is that the father's ברכה bracha is not really
a ברכת המצוה. birchas hamitzvah. The ברכת המצוה birchas hamitzvah is basically
the one that just labels it, that there's a מעשה מצוה ma'aseh
mitzvah here. The other ברכות brachos that are being done here are
ברכות brachos that are done at the time of the מצוה, mitzvah,
but they are more sort of to, you know, they're more ברכת
השבח, birchas hashevach, they're more speaking about the significance of it, and
we're thanking God about it, and therefore for those ברכות brachos they
can come afterwards, they don't have to come before. The ברכת המצוה
birchas hamitzvah that come before just label it immediately as this is
an act of מצוה. mitzvah. Afterwards you can do after you or
certainly when you're in the middle of doing the מצוה, mitzvah, but
right afterwards, if it's a reaction to having done the מצוה mitzvah
and giving thanks and praise like a ברכת השבח, birchas hashevach, then
it comes after and that's normally how these other ברכות brachos are
understood. Now one other point about this before we get on to
the next פרק perek in terms of who is this ידיד מבטן?
yedid mibeten? רש"י rashi says that all of this is יצחק. yitzchak.
Okay יצחק yitzchak was called is the ידיד, yedid, he was sanctified
because אברהם avraham said to him because God said to אברהם, avraham,
you know, I will give my ברית bris with you, שרה sarah
is pregnant will be pregnant and so on. And that all of
it refers to יצחק. yitzchak. תוספות tosfos has a nice דרשה drasha
that all the three אבות avos are referred to. If you look
at תוספות tosfos ידיד מבטן, yedid mibeten, he says אמר רבינו תם
שהוא אברהם אבינו שנקרא ידיד שנאמר מה לידידי בביתי גרישין ממנחות ושלשת
אבות נזכרים חוק בשאירותם, omar rabbeinu tam shehu avraham avinu shenikra yedid
shene'emar mah liyedidi beveysi gerishun mimnachos veshloshes avos nizkarim chok bish'erosam, so
אברהם avraham was sanctified in the womb which is an interesting idea
right? That's like a פסוק posuk by ירמיהו, yirmiyahu, you know, בטרם
אצרך בבטן ידעתיך, beterem etzarcha babeten yedaticha, but anyways the sense of,
okay, and why that be referred to in the context of ברית
מילה? bris milah? But somehow he wants to see all the אבות
avos referred to. So you got אברהם, avraham, then וחוק בשאירותם vechok
bish'erosam is יצחק, yitzchak, וצאצאיו חתם באות ברית קודש שהן vetze'etza'av chasam
be'os bris kodesh shehen יצחק's yitzchak descendants, that's הוא יעקב, hu yaakov,
וצאצאיו vetze'etza'av יעקב yaakov and all the future descendants, הוא בניו. hu
banav. Okay, so therefore you have all the three אבות avos sort
of alluded to here. All right, anyway so there you have the
ברכות brachos introduced in the גמרא, gemara, interestingly not in the משנה,
mishnah, and how you have these different players in terms of who
makes the ברכות brachos and the different functions of what the ברכות
brachos are. Okay, so now the גמרא gemara goes on, and now
we turn to the next פרק. perek. הדרן עלך רבי אליעזר דמילה.
hadran alach rabbi eliezer demilah. So that is the end of הדרן
עלך רבי אליעזר דמילה. hadran alach rabbi eliezer demilah. Okay, now we
have another פרק, perek, another רבי אליעזר. rabbi eliezer. So this is
called תולין tolin because that's the first keyword. רבי אליעזר אומר תולין
את המשמרת ביום טוב. rabbi eliezer omer tolin es hamashmeres beyom tov.
Complete shift from talking about ברית מילה. bris milah. You can suspend
the סיב, siv, a משמרת mashmeres would be something you would do
to sort of a סיב siv so that would take the lees
out of the wine, you know, there would have the little pieces
of grape, you'd pour the wine through it, and the wine would
go through and the other, the you know, the remnants of the
grapes would remain above. So you can suspend it over a vessel
on יום טוב. yom tov. You would basically put like a tight
fitting type of a sieve over
a jar, you know, or can, and you'd pour the wine through
it. So you can put it up on יום טוב. yom tov.
ונותנין לכלי בשבת unosnin likli beshabbos if it's already put on the
jar, on the vessel, you can pour wine through it on שבת.
shabbos. So pouring wine through it raises questions of בורר. borer. What's
the איסור issur about putting it on the vessel? So nothing you
ever would have imagined. The גמרא gemara says it's a type of
a question of like making an אוהל. ohel. Apparently maybe it was
large, you know, and putting this big cover on a type of
a vessel is like making an אוהל, ohel, because it's sort of
like a roof. Okay. וחכמים אומרים, vachachamim omrim, the Sages say,
so wait, you say Tupperware is making a roof?
All right, we'll talk about it. אין תולין את המשמרת ביום טוב.
ein tolin es hamashmeres beyom tov. You can't do it on יום
טוב. yom tov. Even on יום טוב yom tov you can't do
it because although you can do food related issues on יום טוב,
yom tov, this is something that could have been done the day
before, and we don't want you doing things on יום טוב yom
tov you could have been done the day before. ואין נותנין לכלי
בשבת. ve'ein nosnin likli beshabbos. And even if it's already suspended you
can't use it on שבת shabbos because it looks like at least
it looks like בורר. borer. It's not real בורר. borer. אבל נותנין
לכלי ביום טוב. aval nosnin likli beyom tov. On יום טוב yom
tov you can actually use it because you can do food related
issues on יום טוב. yom tov. So the גמרא gemara says like
this, השתא רבי אליעזר אוסופי אהל עראי לא מוסיפינן למיעבד לכתחילה לשבת
שרי? hashta rabbi eliezer osufey ohel arai lo mosfinan lemeved lechatchilah leshabbos
shari? So רבי אליעזר rabbi eliezer says you're allowed to do this
on יום טוב. yom tov. But one minute, we know we assume,
the גמרא gemara takes it for granted that the problem of putting
this sieve cover over this, you know, over this
jar is a problem of like making an אוהל. ohel. We know
from another place that רבי אליעזר Rabbi Eliezer doesn't even allow you
even on יום טוב Yom Tov to make a temporary addition to
an אהל. Ohel. How would he allow you here to make a
new אהל Ohel to begin with? So מאי היא? mai hi? Where
do you know this position of רבי אליעזר? Rabbi Eliezer? דתנן, ditnan,
we taught in the משנה: Mishnah: פקק החלון, pkak hachalon, רבי אליעזר
אומר, Rabbi Eliezer omer, so we had this before, you have the,
you know, the
seal for the window or for maybe רש״י Rashi has it maybe
as a skylight. רבי אליעזר אומר: Rabbi Eliezer omer: בזמן שקשור ותלוי,
bizman shekashur vetalui, if it's tied and suspended, פוקקין בו, pokkin bo,
you can use it to, you know, to stop up the window.
ואם לאו, ve'im lav, and if not, אין פוקקין בו, ein pokkin
bo, you can't because then it's like you're adding something to the
roof or to the wall. וחכמים אומרים: vachachamim omrim: בין כך ובין
כך פוקקין בו, bein kach uvein kach pokkin bo, either way you
can do it. And now maybe that's only שבת, Shabbat, but now
we have the following statement: ואמר רבה בר בר חנה אמר רבי
יוחנן: ve'amar Rabbah bar bar Chana amar Rabbi Yochanan: הכל מודים שאין
עושים אהל עראי בתחילה ביום טוב, hakol modim she'ein osim ohel arai
betchila beYom Tov, everybody agrees that to make a new אהל, Ohel,
even a temporary one, you can't do even on יום טוב, Yom
Tov, ואין צריך לומר בשבת, ve'ein tzarich lomar beShabbat, it goes without
saying on שבת. Shabbat. לא נחלקו אלא להוסיף, lo necheleku ela lehosif,
the whole issue is to add, to make a temporary addition. רבי
אליעזר אומר: Rabbi Eliezer omer: אין מוסיפין ביום טוב, ein mosifin beYom
Tov, even on יום טוב Yom Tov you can't add, ואין צריך
לומר בשבת, ve'ein tzarich lomar beShabbat, and certainly not on שבת. Shabbat.
וחכמים אומרים: vachachamim omrim: מוסיפין בשבת ואין צריך לומר ביום טוב, mosifin
beShabbat ve'ein tzarich lomar beYom Tov, you can do it on שבת
Shabbat and certainly on יום טוב. Yom Tov. So now we've got
the problem, which is that how can רבי אליעזר Rabbi Eliezer allow
you to make an אהל, Ohel, even if it's an אהל עראי,
ohel arai, on יום טוב? Yom Tov? Normally he doesn't even allow
you to add to an אהל עראי ohel arai on יום טוב.
Yom Tov. So the
גמרא Gemara says: רבי אליעזר סבר לה כרבי יהודה. Rabbi Eliezer savar
lei k'Rabbi Yehuda. אה, Ah, he holds like רבי יהודה. Rabbi Yehuda.
דתניא: detanya: בין בין יום טוב לשבת אלא אוכל נפש בלבד, bein
bein Yom Tov leShabbat ela ochel nefesh bilvad, the difference between that
between יום טוב Yom Tov is whether you can do food related,
you know, things. רבי
יהודה מתיר אף מכשירי אוכל נפש. Rabbi Yehuda matir af machshirei ochel
nefesh. So now it's very nice because the same רבי אליעזר Rabbi
Eliezer who allowed you to do מכשירי מילה machshirei milah on שבת,
Shabbat, now we're saying he holds like רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda who
says you can do מכשירי אוכל נפש, machshirei ochel nefesh, not only
things that are directly making the food, but even in the preparatory
stages. So you're right, normally to make an אהל, Ohel, רבי אליעזר
Rabbi Eliezer would not let you do it on שבת, Shabbat, but
you're making an אהל Ohel in order to sift the wine, so
that's okay, that's מכשירי אוכל נפש, machshirei ochel nefesh, and he holds
like רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda that you can do מכשירי אוכל נפש
machshirei ochel nefesh on יום טוב, Yom Tov, and again very nice
like he says you can do מכשירי מילה. machshirei milah. So the
גמרא Gemara says one minute: אימא דשמיען ליה לרבי יהודה במכשירין שאי
אפשר לעשותן מערב יום טוב, eima deshmi'an lei leRabbi Yehuda bemachshirin she'i
efshar la'asotan me'erev Yom Tov, רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda only says that
you can do it if you couldn't have done those preparatory stages
before יום טוב. Yom Tov. במכשירין שאפשר לעשותן מערב יום טוב, bemachshirin
she'efshar la'asotan me'erev Yom Tov, things you could have done before יום
טוב, Yom Tov, מי שמעת ליה? mi shami'at lei? He wouldn't let
you do it on יום טוב. Yom Tov. And here you could
have put this sieve on from ערב יום טוב. erev Yom Tov.
So the גמרא Gemara says: רבי אליעזר עדיפא מדרבי יהודה, Rabbi Eliezer
adifa mid'Rabbi Yehuda, fine, goes one step further. The same way by
ברית מילה, brit milah, he says also by ברית מילה, brit milah,
you know, you could have done stuff even if you could have
theoretically done it before, you can do it on שבת Shabbat itself.
So here too by מכשירי אוכל נפש, machshirei ochel nefesh, רבי אליעזר
Rabbi Eliezer has a very similar position to מכשירי מילה, machshirei milah,
and therefore in principle of course you can't make אהל Ohel on
יום טוב, Yom Tov, but you're allowed to do it here because
it is for the sake of אוכל נפש. ochel nefesh. Okay, we'll
see the rest of this of the משנה, Mishnah, the debate, tomorrow.